<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Westminster-Abbey on the 26th of July, 1685 being the thanksgiving-day for His Majesties victory over the rebels / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1098</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14508864</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14508864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1065:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Westminster-Abbey on the 26th of July, 1685 being the thanksgiving-day for His Majesties victory over the rebels / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Keble ... and Walter Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXIV, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:102449:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen. Maurice</hi> Reverend. <hi>Willielm. Cant.</hi> Archiepiſc. a Sacris.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>for</hi> imparable, <hi>r.</hi> incomparable, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>f.</hi> Monarch, <hi>r.</hi> Monarchy. <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>f.</hi> the, <hi>r.</hi> their.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102449:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>WEST MINSTER-ABBEY</hi> On the <hi>26th.</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1685. BEING THE THANKSGIVING-DAY FOR HIS MAjESTIES VICTORY OVER THE REBELS</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Sommerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at the Earneſt deſire of ſome Friends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Keble</hi> at the <hi>Turks-Head</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> over againſt <hi>Fetter Lane,</hi> and <hi>Walter Davis</hi> in <hi>Amen Corner,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:102449:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102449:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT WESTMINSTER-ABBEY On the <hi>26th.</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1685. BEING THE THANKSGIVINGDAY, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal 124. 6.</bibl>
Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a Prey to their Teeth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE good Providence of God over the Sacred Perſons, and the juſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Princes, in preſerving both from the moſt malicious deſigns of ſo many reſtleſs and ſanguinary Spirits,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102449:3"/>
is one of the moſt ſtupendious Works of Gods Omnipotence that ever he hath ſhew'd ſince the laſt day of the Creation. A Miracle, which was the common ſubject of King <hi>Davids</hi> thankful Meditations, up and down throughout his whole Book of Pſalms, and particularly in <hi>This</hi> Pſalm; where after a moſt humble manner, he doth adore the infinite Mercy and Power of God, for delivering Him and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from the threatning dangers of a freſh <hi>Inſurrection. If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, now may</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſay: If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, when men roſe up againſt us; they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled againſt us: Then the Waters had over whelmed us, the ſtream had gone over our Soul: The proud Waters had gone even over our Soul:</hi> When the Inſurrection was ſo formidable, when the malice of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men was ſo outragious, when their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites were not to be ſatisfied but with ſtreams of Blood; when Ruin was break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon the whole Land like a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Torrent; when, without the immediate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102449:3"/>
help of God, nothing could be expected, but utter Deſolation; when the danger was ſo imminent, and ſeemingly ſo inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that thoſe men of violence thought themſelves as ſure as if the prey they ſought after were already in the Gin; <hi>Then</hi> was the time for <hi>God</hi> to <hi>lay to his Hand,</hi> to make <hi>bare his Arm,</hi> and to gain himſelf Honour by reſcuing Innocence from the <hi>Pit,</hi> as it lay at the <hi>Brink,</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to drop into the <hi>Depth</hi> of Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Pſalm</hi> was <hi>Davids</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> like the Euchariſtical Sacrifice of <hi>Jonah,</hi> after he had been delivered from the belly of the Whale. And that I may not ſpend my time in a curious, but unneceſſary diviſion of the Text, let us fall directly; firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conſideration of <hi>David</hi>'s deliverance, which was the ground of his thankfulneſs, and the purport of the <hi>Pſalm;</hi> and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the ſecond place, to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our <hi>own</hi> deliverance, which is the reaſon of <hi>Our</hi> thankfulneſs, and the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to that deliverance for which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> here bleſt God, indeed Divines can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102449:4"/>
find out any one certain <hi>Aera,</hi> or point of time, where to fix it. But if I may have leave to conjecture, I conceive, that <hi>David</hi> ſpake here in reference to thoſe his <hi>Signal Victories</hi> over ſome Domeſtick Conſpirators, whereof we find a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and grateful Commemoration in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. For ſeveral of the ſame expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions we meet with <hi>there,</hi> which we find in this <hi>Pſalm. There</hi> he ſpake, as he did <hi>Here,</hi> of the <hi>Waves of</hi> Death, of the <hi>Floods</hi> of ungodly Men, of many <hi>Waters,</hi> of <hi>Snares,</hi> of them <hi>that roſe up againſt Him,</hi> and the like. Now it is evident, that in <hi>that</hi> place the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had in his mind, not only the former downfal of <hi>Saul,</hi> but chiefly the <hi>late Victories</hi> which God had given him over two formidable Traitors; the one a diſcontented, yet an Ordinary <hi>Subject,</hi> the other a Darling, but a grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Son.</hi> Let us look a little, I beſeech you, into the Story of both.</p>
            <p>The diſcontented Subject <hi>I</hi> ſpeak of, was that conſiderable man, <hi>Sheba: Sheba</hi> the <hi>Son of Bichri,</hi> as he is called <hi>eight</hi> times together in one Chapter. The Scripture
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102449:4"/>
ſeems to ſet a mark of infamy upon his <hi>Father,</hi> as well as on <hi>Himſelf.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Traitor is named, 'tis always <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba the Sonof Bichri,</hi> as if he were an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary</hi> Rebel. Now <hi>Davids</hi> deliverance, out of the Hands of this Man of <hi>Belial,</hi> was a Work of Gods wonderful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. For, though this Rebellion was not ſo near <hi>Davids</hi> Doors as the other was, yet <hi>David</hi> miſtruſted this Son of <hi>Bichri would do him more harm, than had been done him hitherto,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 6. For the wretch was haughty and enraged: His party was very numerous; yet not more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, than they were perfidious and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal: Men that had ſet up for their King one of <hi>Sauls</hi> Family, while the Houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> followed <hi>David:</hi> Men that conſented to the Kings Reſtauration upon meer neceſſity, and yet would have gone away with the Honour of it: Men that had great expectations from <hi>David,</hi> and becauſe they could not get their <hi>Ends,</hi> and obtain the <hi>Government</hi> of him, took up preſently a mortal grudge againſt him, as if they had <hi>no part, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the Son of</hi> Jeſſe (as they ſpake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102449:5"/>
by way of contempt) and ſo the Alarm was inſtantly taken by them all, <hi>Every man to his Tents, O</hi> Iſrael. This was <hi>Sheba,</hi> and theſe were his <hi>Aſſociates;</hi> a deſperate Leader of a very terrible Defection; nothing being more dangerous to any Prince, than the united malice of Rebellious Spirits, that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, not for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> but either upon <hi>Conſtraint,</hi> or for their <hi>Intereſt</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Yet how ſoon did the hand of God break that dark and threatning Cloud which now covered the greateſt part of <hi>Davids</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? <hi>Joab</hi> indeed <hi>purſued</hi> the Rebel from place to place; and at laſt <hi>hemmed</hi> him in. But the Victory was from <hi>Heaven;</hi> without any battle in the Field, without the perſonal valour of <hi>Joab,</hi> without the loſs of any of <hi>Joabs</hi> Forces was this deliverance wrought: by the contrivance of a woman was <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Head taken off, and caſt over the Wall; by one of the <hi>weaker Veſſels</hi> was the main thing done, <hi>that the Excellency of the Power might be of God, and not of man;</hi> that I may allude to the expreſſion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7.</p>
            <p>But there was a <hi>Greater</hi> deliverance than this, which I doubt not, but <hi>David</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102449:5"/>
thought of, when he penned this Pſalm: A deliverance from a Conſpiracy, that might have <hi>ſwallowed up</hi> the King, and all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were with him, as 'tis ſaid of that Conſpiracy, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 16. the very ſame expreſſion, as is uſed at the <hi>3d. Verſe</hi> of this <hi>Pſalm:</hi> A Conſpiracy that was not only near <hi>Davids</hi> Threſhold, but went to his very <hi>Heart</hi> too, the Conſpiracy of his Son <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> His <hi>bloudy</hi> Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that formerly had been guilty of ſhameful Murder. His <hi>Ambitious</hi> Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> whom none of thoſe Preferments could Content, which would have contented <hi>Sheba;</hi> nothing would ſatisfie him but the <hi>Crown.</hi> His <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful</hi> Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that ſo baſely reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for his <hi>Longings</hi> after him, when he fled from his preſence to <hi>Geſhur,</hi> and for his <hi>Pardon,</hi> for his <hi>Kiſſes</hi> upon his <hi>Return,</hi> and upon that his moſt <hi>ſolemn,</hi> though <hi>artificial</hi> ſubmiſſion at his Fathers Feet. His <hi>perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that no ſooner went out of his Fathers Court, but ran to the Gates <hi>to ſteal away the hearts of his Fathers Subjects</hi> with ſuch <hi>mean</hi> addreſſes to the Populace, <hi>O that I were made Judg</hi> (meaning, King) <hi>in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102449:6"/>
the Land.</hi> His <hi>hypocritical</hi> Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that pretending a deſire to perform his <hi>Vow,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the <hi>Throne,</hi> and under colour of <hi>Religion</hi> raiſed an open and barefac't <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> This was ſuch a dreadful Conſpiracy, as made <hi>David</hi> himſelf, though a man of ſuch Proweſs and Conduct, preſently <hi>to flee for his Life.</hi> For ſo it was that <hi>Abſalom,</hi> what with the gracefulneſs and beauty of his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> what with his <hi>Popularity,</hi> and what with other ſiniſter and ſordid Artifices, had inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated himſelf ſtrangly into peoples Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; <hi>the hearts of the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>were after him,</hi> ſaith the Scripture; ſo that the Conſpiracy was <hi>ſtrong; the buſineſs was laid very broad,</hi> for the <hi>People increaſed continually</hi> with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> though at the <hi>Firſt</hi> he was but two hundred Men ſtrong, as we read, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. Had not the hand of God, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Seas, govern'd and over-rul'd this deſign, the King had been utterly undone, and all his Loyal Subjects that clave to him: Such a violent agitation were diſaffected People in then, that they were ready to flow to him from all Quarters, like the meeting and inundation of many Rivers to make a Deluge.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102449:6"/>
            <p>But that which made this Conſpiracy the <hi>more</hi> terrible, was <hi>this,</hi> that <hi>Achitophel</hi> was in the head of it. <hi>Achitophel,</hi> that had ſerved to corrupt and debauch the young man, <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and had miniſtred to his Luſts. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel,</hi> that Falſe and Treacherous Villain, that had been one of <hi>Davids Counſellors;</hi> nay, the <hi>Preſident</hi> of his Council, as 'tis plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimated, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 37. 34. <hi>Achitophel,</hi> that dexterous man at <hi>wickedneſs;</hi> ſuch a cunning and crafty Politician, that he was lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as infallible, as an <hi>Oracle. Achitophel,</hi> that was ſo maliciouſly ſet againſt the King, that nothing would ſatisfie him, but the Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his <hi>Perſon. Achitophel,</hi> that hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Traytor, and curſed Reprobate, that when his Counſel and Bloudy endeavours would not take, <hi>fled for it</hi> preſently, and through anguiſh and vexation hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: (A ſad End indeed, for any Rebel to be his own Executioner, though in ſome caſes 'tis pity that an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> an <hi>inveterate,</hi> and <hi>adviſing</hi> Rebel ſhould ever die in his <hi>Bed.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the higheſt Treaſon was formed by ſuch working heads, when 'twas condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102449:7"/>
by ſuch Politick Counſels, when 'twas Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by ſuch deſperate Inſtruments, when it proſper'd on a ſuddain by ſuch ſucceſsful ſtratagems nothing could be expected, but the Kings inevitable ruine, had not the hand of <hi>God</hi> been more concern'd in the cauſe, than the hand of <hi>Joab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein was manifeſted the great power of God, that notwithſtanding all theſe Arts, Enterpriſes, and deſired Events of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the whole frame of the Conſpiracy was daſht down in a moment, the King was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, <hi>Peace</hi> was reſtored, the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was freed from commotions and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and all this, by the unexpected and ſurprizing death of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who, as God, would have it, was <hi>caught in a Wood;</hi> and hung by his Locks upon a Tree; to ſhew the World what a Reward all they deſerve, that take up Arms, and Rebel againſt their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You have now ſeen ſome of <hi>Davids</hi> deliverances; I mean his deliverances from <hi>Home-bred</hi> dangers, from Enemies that were in his <hi>own Country,</hi> in his <hi>own Boſome;</hi> which, as I conceive, <hi>David</hi> had an immediate eye
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102449:7"/>
upon in this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where he bleſt the God of his Salvation, that he and his people were not <hi>delivered as a Prey unto their Teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed in the next place, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our <hi>own</hi> deliverances, which is the neceſſary ſubject of our Meditations this day. I know not any deliverances, that can come <hi>nearer</hi> (perhaps not ſo <hi>near)</hi> to thoſe of <hi>David,</hi> either for the <hi>Quality,</hi> or for the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of them, then thoſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful deliverances from ſo many <hi>Sheba</hi>'s and <hi>Achitophels,</hi> which God hath from time to time wrought for this Nation: Perhaps no Age, no State, no Hiſtory can ſhew the <hi>Like</hi> inſtances of his good Providence; ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied hath his Goodneſs been to <hi>our</hi> Princes, as if he had entailed his Mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Them,</hi> as he did upon <hi>David, and upon his ſeed for evermore.</hi> 'Tis true (a moſt ſad and ſhameful Truth, God knows) ſuch was the monſtrous impiety of the Laſt Age, that it afforded one unpreſidented, unparallel'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Gods wrath, when that imparable Monarch, the Glory of our Reformation, and the Honour of the World, was forced to bow his head down, and to fall a Sacrifice
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102449:8"/>
to the Luſts of the moſt barbarous Villains, as if God had forſaken him. Yet I cannot tell, but that God, who draweth Good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times out of the greateſt Evil, did in that terrible juncture deſign to ſhew men the exceſſive <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of their Follies, in throwing away a Felicity, always to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on, but hardly ever to be <hi>recover'd</hi> to the Worlds End. However, that ſome <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation</hi> might be made for that <hi>ſuperlative</hi> (and otherwiſe <hi>irreparable)</hi> loſs, by the due <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi> and after <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of his Poſterity, God hath <hi>multiplied</hi> thoſe temporal Glories upon the <hi>Sons,</hi> which he took from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and gave him a Bleſſed Eternity in <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> for. And to let the World ſee, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance is criminal even when 'tis proſperous, and to puniſh Rebellion in a ſecond Age, tho' it eſcaped in the Firſt, God hath delivered the two Royal Brothers <hi>from ſix troubles and ſeven,</hi> though <hi>Sheba</hi> and <hi>Abſalom,</hi> with their wicked Confederates, joyned hand in hand to Execute a Conſpiracy, which had been long a forming by the Serpentine ſubtilty of a twining and party colour'd <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Deliverance was manifeſtly the work
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102449:8"/>
               <hi>God.</hi> For firſt our dangers were ſo immenſe, and yet ſo cloſe and privy, that it both paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſagacity, and exceeded the reach of humane Force to prevent them; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could deliver us from them, but the Power and Wiſdome of Almighty God. What were the <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> but the moſt da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and deſperate Villains? Men of the moſt deſperate <hi>Principles,</hi> ready and diſpos'd for the moſt deſperate <hi>undertakings;</hi> and either ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with the guilt of <hi>former</hi> Crimes, or ſo linked together in the Communion of <hi>New</hi> ones, that nothing leſs could be expected, then the utmoſt of thoſe miſchiefs which are always acted by men of the moſt deſperate <hi>Fortunes?</hi> And what was the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> it ſelf, but a long ſtudied, and now ripe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, to draw in upon us a whole Deluge of Blood, to overwhelm Prince and People, with final ſlaughter, to deſtroy the very Name, as well as to ſtifle all further efforts of Loyalty, to bury our Monarch beyond all hopes of a Reſurrection, to ingulph the Church in an eternal Chaos, ſo that you ſhould hardly have ſeen the very Ruins of it, to daſh down at once the whole frame of the preſent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102449:9"/>
Government, and to leave it to Time, and Fortune, and the Deciſion of the Sword, what other Model ſhould be ſet up? And what would have been at the end of all this, but Irreligion and Atheiſm, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the moſt diſmal Confuſions, and a perpetual War, till by weak'ning and killing one another, each Party muſt have given a <hi>Forreign</hi> Power the faireſt opportunity of Invading and Captivating all. Nothing could deſtroy ſuch a bulky, ſuch a barbarous Deſign, but the Arm of God, whoſe <hi>extroar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> providence is then wont <hi>viſibly</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe, when dangers are ſo Immenſe; ſo Imminent, and otherwiſe Inevitable. And the Truth is, the Conſpiracy was too <hi>great</hi> to <hi>proſper,</hi> too exceſſively monſtrous to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but <hi>Atheiſts</hi> promiſes of <hi>ſucceſs;</hi> the Mercy of God being ſuch, that amidſt all our <hi>Corrections,</hi> he hath ſtill kept us from <hi>Ruin,</hi> and has always ſaved us from the <hi>Ax,</hi> though we have been often delivered moſt deſervedly to the <hi>Rod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Again; the Conſpiracy <hi>was laid ſo very broad</hi> (as one of the Criminals himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt) that there is little reaſon to doubt, but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102449:9"/>
that innumerable numbers of diſaffected men in all parts of this great Iſland, divers of the moſt <hi>Potent,</hi> many the moſt <hi>Active,</hi> all the moſt <hi>Violent</hi> of the Faction, were more or leſs actually engaged to carry the Deſign on; ſo that had not that good God won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully interpoſed, who commands the hearts, and ſtilleth the madneſs of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by his own ſecret, and unaccountable, but yet over-ruling and efficacious power, in all humane probability no way could have been left for innocence to eſcape. And when the Rebellion was now <hi>begun</hi> by the moſt <hi>Forward</hi> of the party, that gave the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm to the reſt, who only waited for an <hi>invitation;</hi> to <hi>diſtract</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> Kingdom, <hi>Sheba</hi> had ſo poſted himſelf in <hi>one</hi> part of it, and <hi>Abſalom</hi> in <hi>another,</hi> that all ſuch whoſe hearts were after <hi>both,</hi> had their choice gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them of repairing unto <hi>either,</hi> had not God reſtrained and dampt their ſpirits, and made even reſolute men, Cowards. This we muſt needs aſcribe to the particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God; eſpecially if we do conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that thoſe <hi>ordinary</hi> Forces throughout the Nation, on which we confided for the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102449:10"/>
curbing and ſuppreſſing of <hi>Rebels,</hi> were, (for the moſt part) what through cowardiſe, what through perfidiouſneſs, and what through both, much prepar'd, and much more deſirous themſelves to turn <hi>Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not but that God permitted the <hi>Foeces</hi> of the people to gather together into a <hi>conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> (nay, I muſt call it, becauſe we once thought it, a <hi>formidable)</hi> body; for never is there an inundation without a great ſcum. But yet, ſuch was the good Providence of God to us, that all this was, more for our Terrour, then to our Injury: that by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us ſenſible of our <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> God might ſhew us our danger; which had it not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared at our Doors, might have made no more impreſſion upon us, than a Dream in the Night.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And in this, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the Hand of God was moſt plainly ſeen, that after ſo many preparations on the one ſide, after ſo many terrours on the other, and after ſo many <hi>uncertainties</hi> on both, the Scales were turn'd ſo in a moment, that we no ſooner heard of a <hi>Conflict,</hi> than we were ſure of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102449:10"/>
a <hi>Victory,</hi> and that in ſuch a <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> juncture, that we might have thought our ſelves happy, might have bleſt God for but a <hi>Drawn</hi> Battle; they that ſhall duely conſider what a condition the Kings affairs was in that <hi>Fatal</hi> Night, (for it was the moſt Fatal Night-work that ever <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> had in hand) how diſproportionable his Majeſties Forces were in Number, how ſecure they were, like ſo many good Conſciences at their Repoſe, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly fire and Sword came againſt them, how <hi>ſilently</hi> he <hi>ſtole</hi> upon them like a <hi>Thief,</hi> whoſe deſign was to plunder a whole Kingdom; and yet how <hi>ſuddenly</hi> that deſperate engagment ended, I do not ſay in a Victory, but in an utter defeat and <hi>overthrow</hi> of the <hi>whole Faction;</hi> they muſt needs look upon it as a <hi>Miraculous</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and grant the providence of God to have been as viſible then in the <hi>Preſervation</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> as it had been before in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> himſelf. Lord! how in a <hi>moment</hi> was that great work done which the Government had been labouring at for ſo many years, and yet unſucceſsfully?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102449:11"/>
How <hi>ſoon</hi> were all the <hi>Councels of</hi> Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel <hi>turned into fooliſhneſs;</hi> and all the Arts and Machinations of his numerous Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents bruſht down all at once like a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web, in the twinkling of an Eye? After ſo many deſigns againſt the Monarchy and the Church, which had been ſo Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly, and ſo deeply laid; after ſo many cloſe and Treaſonable conſultations that had been held; after ſuch along trade of Perjuries, that to the wounding of their conſciences, and to the ſcandal of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had been practiced: after ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry that had been uſed in lying, Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and debauching the World with wicked Principles; after ſo much pains that had been taken in ſetting up Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to overlay and ſtifle the Laws; after ſo much villainous Hypocriſie, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate Souls had been guilty of even before the Altar of God; after ſo many correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondences that had been maintain'd thro'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe Kingdoms to hew down all the pillars thereof; after ſuch a train of Arts, which they had been laying ſo many years to begin and carry on a Rebellion; after ſuch a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102449:11"/>
vaſt expence of time and Mony; <hi>(Mony</hi> like that which <hi>Judas</hi> received, that may coſt even the <hi>Creditors</hi> their <hi>Necks)</hi> after all this, I ſay, and a great deal more, the whole controverſie was ended as it were at a <hi>Blow,</hi> by a <hi>few</hi> men, by an hours puſh; and ſo, that thoſe very methods which they uſed for the <hi>Ruin,</hi> have effectually ſerved to the <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of the Throne; they have made our Prince (though againſt their own Wills) <hi>a glorious King</hi> indeed, and Us his faithful Subjects, an happy and ſafe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And all, by the good Providence of our God, who for his Mercy ſake govern'd and over-rul'd even <hi>Midnight</hi> ſurpriſes, and in that <hi>critical</hi> and moſt <hi>dangerous</hi> juncture kept us All from being the prey to the fury, or cruelties of thoſe <hi>Abaddons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And yet, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the <hi>Providence</hi> of God did not ſtop here; but as his <hi>bare</hi> and <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched Arm</hi> had now unexpectedly defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe villainous Enterpriſes, ſo to Crown the Victory after a ſignal manner, his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance purſued and overtook the <hi>Men,</hi> even the moſt <hi>Principal</hi> Traytors, to deliver up thoſe to the <hi>Law,</hi> who had eſcaped the <hi>Sword.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102449:12"/>
This was a <hi>ſingular</hi> and very <hi>remarkable</hi> Work of God; becauſe on this our <hi>future</hi> Peace and Felicity did depend: and to ſee how ſtrangely God doth ſometimes bring his great purpoſes to paſs, this <hi>Laſt,</hi> this <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> Work was done after a moſt <hi>Providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> manner, and by the <hi>meaneſt</hi> and moſt <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> Inſtruments. For as that <hi>Sheba</hi> of the <hi>North</hi> was after a <hi>Months</hi> Invaſion, taken at laſt by <hi>three Servants,</hi> in the <hi>Water;</hi> ſo that <hi>Abſalom</hi> of the <hi>Weſt</hi> was after his <hi>Months</hi> Invaſion, or thereabout, caught alſo by <hi>three</hi> Men of the like <hi>Figure</hi> and <hi>Condition,</hi> and that like <hi>Abſalom</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> in a <hi>Wood,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Brakes and Trees; and hereby God ſhewed his juſt diſpleaſure againſt <hi>All</hi> the Rebels <hi>both</hi> ways, by expoſing the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable of them to <hi>Diſgrace</hi> and <hi>Shame,</hi> as well as by bringing them to capital puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And thus by a <hi>Wonderful</hi> and an <hi>uninterrupted</hi> courſe of Gods bleſſed provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he hath in a very <hi>ſhort</hi> time wrought one of the greateſt Deliverances for us, and our Poſterity; theſe having been (we hope) the <hi>Laſt Efforts</hi> of that wicked <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which for many years hath made ſuch miſchiefs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102449:12"/>
in the World, but (God be bleſſed) was brought at length to it's <hi>extream Agonies,</hi> and is now <hi>Dead: Dead,</hi> and I hope <hi>Buried,</hi> till the day of <hi>Final</hi> Reckoning, when it's more <hi>valiant</hi> Patriots will riſe up in judgment, and <hi>upbraid</hi> theſe for the leſs fortunate ſucceſſes of their more <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>Notorious</hi> Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
            <p>That I have thus particularly obſerved the ſeveral ſteps of Gods Providence in this caſe; is not only to expreſs mine own deep and humble Senſe of thoſe manifold Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which never fail us; or to quicken the like Senſe in you, and to excite the Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of us all, to give due Teſtimonies and Expreſſions of the moſt Religious Hearts; of Hearts <hi>Penitent</hi> for thoſe Sins which drew the point of the Sword upon us, and <hi>Thankful</hi> for our ſpeedy and effectual Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from it.</p>
            <p>Though theſe are Euchariſtical acts, very ſuitable to the purport of this day; very neceſſary to be performed by us, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodneſs of God to us, <hi>when we were in trouble:</hi> yet there are three <hi>other</hi> things, which I would by way of practical Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102449:13"/>
draw out of this whole conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and methinks we are ſo plainly taught them by this our late Deliverance, as if God <hi>himſelf</hi> did purpoſely intend to direct us to theſe <hi>three</hi> things with his own <hi>Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That we carry in our minds a <hi>Fixt and Awful Remembrance of a Deity.</hi> Good God! That ever <hi>Atheiſm</hi> ſhould prevail in ſuch a Land as this, where not only all <hi>Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Arguments</hi> have been uſed to prove a Being infinitely Wiſe, Juſt, and Good, to Preſide over the World, but moreover where the <hi>Preſence</hi> of God hath been ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſo long, and in all the viciſſitudes and changes of this Sublunary World, <hi>ſo conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſeen and <hi>manifeſted,</hi> as if he had taken up his <hi>Abode</hi> with us, as if he had ſaid of this Kingdom, as he did of <hi>Zion,</hi> Pſal. 132. 14. <hi>This is my reſt for ever; here will I dwell, for I have a delight therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I may ſay truly, but to our great ſhame, that ſince the Creation of the Univerſe there never was ſuch an Athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Generation, no not in the moſt dark, in the moſt diſtant, in the moſt infidel parts of the World, as this Nation hath
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102449:13"/>
groaned under of late years. And yet 'tis obſervable, though it be very ſtrange, that none among us have pretended grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concernment for the Reformation, for the intereſt, for the ſecurity of our eſtabliſht Religion, than thoſe who have bid open defiance to all Religion whatſoever. Men of the moſt Licentious Lives, of the moſt ſeared conſciences, of the moſt profligate Reputation: Open Drunkards, profeſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, Notorious Cheats, Forſworn Rebels, Impudent Lyars, perfidious Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and but the other day Scoffers at God, and at the very ſhew of piety. 'Tis enough to move the meekeſt, the moſt patient man on Earth to conſider, what foreheads of ſteel and Adamant thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Wretches have, that could take the confidence thus to gull and impoſe upon the World by a ſeeming zeal for <hi>Religion;</hi> and eſpecially, that when they were now up in Arms for it, they ſhould Raviſh Virgins, commit Sacriledge, and drink the moſt vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lainous Healths in the Bowls of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and even before the Altar of <hi>God:</hi> ſuch a barbarous profanation, as <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102449:14"/>
would have dreaded amidſt all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines.</p>
            <p>'Tis no wonder that the righteous God did preſently write <hi>Mene, Mene,</hi> upon the Plaiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Walls, and made a very <hi>ſhort</hi> Work with that Kingdom, which they thought to have had; for who could think, that ſuch monſtrous Impieties could proſper? And when God did on a ſuddain, and after ſuch a Providential and Signal manner, blaſt the deſigns of thoſe wicked men, he did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vindicate his own <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and gain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Honour</hi> upon thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> that were Rebels againſt <hi>Himſelf,</hi> as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>Soveraign;</hi> but he did that too, which was enough to Convince even the <hi>Actors</hi> of thoſe wickedneſſes, that <hi>verily there is a Reward for the Righteous,</hi> and <hi>that there is a God that Judgeth the Earth.</hi> In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect God was ſo kind and good to thoſe his <hi>Enemies</hi> too, that he made their very <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments</hi> to <hi>Inſtruct</hi> them, and took a direct courſe to convince the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> by defeating, and plagging and delivering up the <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> I pray God, all ſuch of them as yet ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive may be throughly ſenſible of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102449:14"/>
and make a Chriſtian uſe of it, <hi>while it is called to day;</hi> and that all ſuch as have not God in their <hi>thoughts,</hi> may learn once to make him their <hi>Fear,</hi> by impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidering the <hi>Exemplary</hi> fall of <hi>Abſalom</hi> (if I have not done him too <hi>Great</hi> an Honor in calling him <hi>Abſalom,</hi> whoſe <hi>perſidious</hi> and <hi>mean</hi> ſpirit never argued him to be the ſon of a <hi>Prince.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As for thoſe, in the <hi>Second</hi> place, who <hi>own</hi> and <hi>acknowledg</hi> a Diety, and yet are apt to ſtagger (as many among us of late have done) in their belief of the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> as if our truſting in God were a thing of ſmall value, as if we and our Religion were in a dangerous caſe, as if ordinary means would do us no good, and as if nothing but <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>indirect</hi> courſe could ſecure our Civil and <hi>Sacred</hi> Intereſts; in the Name of God let ſuch men ſeriouſly reflect upon this our <hi>Late Deliverance,</hi> and thereby learn that excellent Wiſdom, in all Caſes and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, <hi>ſtill to commit themſelves to God in well doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which was the <hi>Ground</hi> (or, at leaſt, the <hi>Pretence)</hi> for the late Rebellion, was this.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102449:15"/>
Unreaſonable Jealouſie, which ſome weak men have entertain'd, that the Ark of God, which hath been (bleſſed be God) fixed in this Kingdom, hath been ſo Glorious ſince the Reformation, is now in a tottering, in a falling Condition, ſo that nothing but <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>Armed Hands</hi> can ſupport it. This, you know, is the Common Plea, which Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and Rebels uſe for their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to, and reſiſtance of the Lords Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now I am apt to believe, that in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this late marvellous Deliverance for us, one of Gods good purpoſes was, to <hi>ſignifie</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> that as he hath been all along with our <hi>Fathers,</hi> ſo He is ſtill with <hi>Us,</hi> that in all circumſtances and junctures, he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to take care of us, and that his good Providence ſhall not be wanting to us, if we be not wanting to our Duty, but adorn our Faith with ſincere obedience to Himſelf and his Vice-gerent, and ſo put our Truſt and Confidence in him, as good and honeſt hearted Chriſtians ought to do.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to deal plainly with you; for the condition of the Times requires plain-dealing.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102449:15"/>
            <p>It hath been generally believed, that a Prince, who is in the communion of <hi>another</hi> Church, muſt needs endeavour the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Eſtabliſht</hi> Religion, if it be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from his own. Men are ready to think it muſt <hi>neceſſarily</hi> be thus, and that it cannot poſſibly be <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> But this is a very great <hi>miſtake:</hi> and to prove that it is ſo, I appeal to a moſt memorable ſtory, that I perceive is not taken notice of, and yet the truth of it is acknowledg'd by one, that is well known to be of <hi>Republican</hi> Principles, and that a while ago wrote a very Seditious Book, to <hi>Subvert</hi> our <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and to reduce our Government to the <hi>Venetian</hi> form; I mean, the Author of <hi>Plato Redivivus.</hi> That very man tells us <hi>(pag.</hi> 207) that a few years ſince, a Duke of <hi>Hanover</hi> was reconciled to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and even went to <hi>Rome</hi> to abjure the Proteſtant Religion. Yet upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home, he lived and govern'd as he did <hi>before,</hi> without the leaſt animoſity of his <hi>Subjects</hi> for the change he had made, and without any endeavour of his to introduce any change in his <hi>Government</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> but reigned peaceably fourteen years, and then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102449:16"/>
dying left the Eſtabliſht Government and Religion entire to his Brother, the Biſhop of <hi>Oſnaburg,</hi> who was a Proteſtant. Here now is plain <hi>experience</hi> and matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> which ſhews that 'tis very <hi>poſſible</hi> for a Prince to Reign very quietly and peaceably over a Church, that is of a different Faith in ſome things from his own. Conſider this inſtance well: it may be a good means, by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, to remove thoſe in ordinate jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, which are ſo deſtructive both of the Kings and the Peoples peace, and which we ſhould carefully <hi>ſtifle</hi> for that reaſon; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince our <hi>Prince</hi> hath given us ſo many <hi>Solemn Aſſurances,</hi> and in all his <hi>actions</hi> hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath given <hi>Real Demonſtrations</hi> of his ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. A <hi>Prince,</hi> not of <hi>Abſaloms</hi> temper, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, fraudulent, falſe;</hi> but one of that <hi>True Honor</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> that he never yet <hi>deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> any part of mankind, and I am perſwaded never <hi>will;</hi> unleſs it be in <hi>one</hi> point; I mean as to their <hi>Fears:</hi> thoſe indeed, he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived already, and truly the World is bound with all <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> to forgive him that.</p>
            <p>But I was ſpeaking of the <hi>Providence of God</hi> and of caſting our ſelves upon it in all Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102449:16"/>
and Conditions. And do but conſider, I beſeech you, what is it, but the <hi>Providence</hi> of God, that all <hi>Princes</hi> and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple live by: And what is it, but that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Providence</hi> which hath made our <hi>Prince</hi> and us to out-live theſe late dangers, which threatned us with no leſs, then utter and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſs Deſtruction? Here we have had <hi>freſh</hi> Experience of Gods over-ruling <hi>Providence</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> in a Deliverance, that may trouble an inquiſitive Hiſtorian to find out it's paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel; if you take it all together, and conſider how black the Cloud over our Heads was, and how ſuddainly it increaſed from the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a mans hand, and what Aſſurances ſo many Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> went upon, and how ready the hearts of vaſt multitudes more were to run to their aſſiſtance; and what En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements they would have had upon the leaſt ſucceſs, and how <hi>near</hi> that Succeſs was; and yet how this great <hi>Complication</hi> of dangers was broken, diſſipated, and utterly deſtroyed in a <hi>moment,</hi> in the turn of an <hi>hand,</hi> in the twinkling of an <hi>eye,</hi> as if God was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us a <hi>new</hi> world after the ſame manner he made <hi>this,</hi> when <hi>he only ſpake the word, and it was done.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102449:17"/>
            <p>What can there be more, to encourage us to an intire and conſtant dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the good Providence of God? Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if we remember what <hi>David</hi> ſaid, when he reflected upon that ſatisfaction and eaſe of mind which was the reſult of his <hi>Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> This I had, <hi>becauſe I have kept thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> Pſal. 119. 56. And this, perhaps, <hi>We</hi> have had too as the Reward of <hi>our</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. For though we are far from ever owning the doctrine of Merits, yet 'tis not immodeſt to think, that God, who hath a <hi>Reſpect unto the Meek, Regard to the Lowly,</hi> and a <hi>Favour to all ſuch as are true of heart,</hi> hath in this our late Deliverance ſhew'd ſome regard and favour to <hi>our Zeal</hi> in the late Times for true Allegiance, Juſtice, and Honeſty, when others did not care what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil they did, as long as it tended unto good. Though for a good Conſcience-ſake we ran the greateſt hazards, and were wrapt up in the greateſt difficulties, and yet had but very little Encouragements before us, yet (bleſſed be God) we were mindful of our Duty, and Reſolved to Live and Die by it, and acted like good Chriſtians, though ſeemingly at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102449:17"/>
all manner of diſadvantage; and all this upon that firm truſt and confidence we had in the Providence of our God. And now we ſee his Providence hath not failed us, nor have our hopes made us aſhamed; but God hath marvellouſly done the bleſſed Work for us, and ſtrangely reſtored us to a bleſſed condition, while his juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have been ſuch upon the Enemies of our peace, that all thoſe Arts and Methods which they employed for <hi>Our</hi> ruin, have after a moſt ſtupendious and unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner turned to their <hi>Own.</hi> I dare ſay, that if you trace over all thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed practices which they have uſed for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years laſt paſt to undermine the Throne, to blow up the Church, to deſtroy and overthrow All; you will find that true, which <hi>David</hi> obſerved of ſuch men in his days, that <hi>they are ſunk down in the pit that they made;</hi> that <hi>in the Net, which they had hid, their own foot is taken; that they are caught in the devices which they themſelves imagined for others, that they are fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ditch, that they digged with their own hands; that their miſchiefs are returned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102449:18"/>
their own heads, and their violent dealings come down upon their own Pates.</hi> Bleſſed be God that it is ſo; it is marvellous in our eyes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly therefore, that I may conclude all by applying my ſelf to ſuch as <hi>hate</hi> the ſins of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>unfaithfulneſs;</hi> let the conſideration of this aſtoniſhing deliverance, ſtrengthen our hopes and confidence ſtill, that <hi>God will perfect that good work which he hath wrought in us.</hi> I was <hi>upright before God,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> upon the conſideration of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, in Pſalm 18. <hi>Therefore hath the Lord recompenſed me according to my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, according to the cleanneſs of my hands in his eye ſight. With the merciful thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf merciful; with an upright man thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf upright; With the pure, thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf pure, and with the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thou wilt learn frowardneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The courſe of Gods Providence is to go along with men in their <hi>own</hi> ways, to deal with them as they carry themſelves towards that Rule of Life, which he hath laid before them; and to protect, or caſt them out of his hands, according as their Truſt, or their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102449:18"/>
diſtruſt is in his providence. Therefore if we do but unanimouſly apply our hearts carefully to obſerve his Will, and Act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of honeſty and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we have no Reaſon to doubt, but God will not only preſerve that eſtabliſht Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Religion which are ſo <hi>dear</hi> to us, but will moreover <hi>fix</hi> and <hi>re-ſettle</hi> both upon ſuch ſure foundations, that we ſhall be once again the honour and envy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</p>
            <p>As far as I have obſerved, the whole Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>England</hi> doth not afford us an inſtance of Gods providence that can come any thing <hi>near</hi> that account which relates to our preſent Soveraign and his Royal Brother and <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor</hi> of ever bleſſed Memory; unleſs it be that ſingle ſtory of <hi>King Alfred the Great.</hi> A Prince of that Learning, Wiſdom, Clemency, Sweetneſs of Nature, and other ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Vertues, as really made him an <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> to the Throne. And yet that excellent Prince was once reduced to thoſe miſerable ſtraights, partly by the Invaſion of Enemies from abroad, and partly through the treachery of Rebels and Deſerters at
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102449:19"/>
home, that he was forced to put himſelf into the diſguiſe once of a common <hi>Soldier,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time of an <hi>Herds man,</hi> and at laſt to <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcond</hi> for a conſiderable time in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> in a poor Cottage among <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Moors;</hi> a ſad and woful place for a <hi>Crowned</hi> Head to reſt in: And yet, ſuch was his Religious dependence upon God, that though he was forſaken by his friends, environed with his Enemies, and brought to thoſe extreme and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful neceſſities, that his Mother and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf were hardly able to <hi>ſubſiſt,</hi> yet he doubted not but providence would one day <hi>reſtore</hi> him to his <hi>juſt Grandieur.</hi> And ſo it was, that in that very <hi>mean Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in that moſt <hi>Obſcure Place</hi> he began the <hi>Recovery</hi> of his Fortunes; and 'tis obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the <hi>Place</hi> was in thoſe very <hi>Moors</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> between <hi>Taunton</hi> and <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water: There he began the new</hi> foundation of his Kingdom <hi>raiſing</hi> it on ſtill by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, till in a little time he became the <hi>ſole</hi> and <hi>abſolute</hi> Monarch of this Nation, and made it a moſt <hi>flouriſhing</hi> Kingdom, and gave many the moſt <hi>Excellent Laws</hi> that we enjoy at <hi>this Hour.</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102449:19"/>
We know, too well, to what Miſeries, Dangers, and reproachful Neceſſities, the Sins of this Nation expoſed the Off-ſpring of that <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Incomparable</hi> Martyr, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, <hi>of whom the World was not worthy.</hi> I need not ſpeak of the <hi>Royal Oak,</hi> nor of the reſt of thoſe ſtraights, which were not <hi>unlike</hi> thoſe of King <hi>Alfred.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all thoſe difficulties, the Providence of God hath been over that our <hi>late,</hi> and this our <hi>preſent</hi> Soveraign; ſo that he hath not only preſerv'd them <hi>Both</hi> out of the hands of their bloud-thirſty and barbarous Enemies, but hath moreover ſhew'd his <hi>Power</hi> in <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting</hi> the Throne from ſo <hi>Low,</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Lofty</hi> State, as if <hi>Alfred the Great</hi> ſate in it <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:</hi> and this we owe to the ſingular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God in giving his Majeſty this moſt memorable Conqueſt over <hi>His</hi> and <hi>Our</hi> Enemies at <hi>King</hi> Alfreds <hi>quarters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As we are to bleſs God for his unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mercy, ſo let us ever put our firm hope and confidence in him; being careful ſtill to act like good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and honeſt hearted <hi>Subjects,</hi> and then not doubting, but that <hi>all things will work together</hi> (as hitherto they have done) <hi>for our Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:102449:20"/>
I conclude all with thoſe Triumphant expreſſions Apocal. 19. <hi>Hallelujah, Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Glory, and Honour, and Power be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto the Lord our God, for True and Righteous are his Judgments.</hi> To him be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by us and all Churches of Chriſt, all Honour, Thankſgiving, and Adoration for evermore: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102449:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
